These next five videos I'm going to
be covering everything Vitamin B12.
How fast B12 deficiency can set in,
the earliest signs to watch out for,
why standard blood tests can miss it,
and just how dangerous
it can be left untreated.
Most importantly,
the best way to protect yourself.
"How Long Does It Take to Become Vitamin B12 Deficient
and What Are the Symptoms?"
For those eating
plant-based diets,
encouragement
of vitamin B12 supplementation
cannot be overemphasized.
What happens
if you don’t get enough B12?
Well, the vitamin is necessary
for the synthesis of DNA,
so, a deficiency in B12
can cause pretty much anything.
Brain problems,
psychiatric problems,
sensory problems,
constitutional problems,
muscle problems,
nerve problems.
It can also cause
clotting disorders
and bleeding disorders.
It can make people catatonic,
hallucinate, psychotic,
even suicidal.
One patient
got electroshock therapy
before they realized,
"Oops, he was just
B12 deficient."
Even more tragic are
life-threatening manifestations
of B12 deficiency in infants
when their moms
aren’t supplementing;
coma, respiratory failure,
severe brain damage.
Vitamin B12 deficiency
in pregnancy
is a diagnosis not to miss.
I’ve done B12 videos like this
over and over again
over the years.
Can we just stick
to the consensus
clinical guidelines
on preventing,
diagnosing,
and treating B12 deficiency?
No, we can’t
because there aren’t any.
There are lots
of recommendations out there
but little robust evidence
to back them up.
They’re based
more on assumptions
than solid clinical evidence.
That’s why you’ll see
papers like this,
"How I Treat
Vitamin B12 Deficiency."
Why should we care what
some random doctor does?
Because there aren’t
a lot of clear-cut answers
everyone agrees upon.
For example,
it is currently unknown
how long it takes
for vitamin B12 deficiency
to occur in someone
going completely plant-based
without supplementing with B12
or B12-fortified foods.
This textbook
suggested it might take
as long as 10 or 20 years,
but that was based
on a study of baboons
and a single case report.
On the flipside
are those suggesting
we can see evidence
of a functional B12 deficiency
within four weeks,
but if you look at that source,
that’s not right either.
Three years is a common
time frame we hear,
but that’s just from this
70-year-old autopsy study
where a back-of-the-envelope
calculation said
that if the average liver weighs
like three pounds (1.35 kg),
and B12 is stored in the liver,
and there’s a certain amount
of B12 per gram,
then the average liver
would contain enough
for three years,
but that’s just all in theory.
If we look at people
undergoing a type
of bariatric surgery
that messes with B12 absorption,
we start seeing problems
within just a few months
in terms of impaired metabolism,
a rise in methylmalonic acid
and homocysteine,
two compounds that are normally
cleared, in part, by B12.
This challenges the concept
that liver stores of B12
were sufficient
for long-term maintenance
of adequate B12 status.
Here’s an interesting
recent case.
A vegan who had been taking B12
decided to stop it
for undisclosed reasons.
This allowed
for a natural experiment.
Though his blood levels of B12
stayed within normal limits,
his homocysteine
went through the roof.
We like to see it
below 12 µmol/L,
but it jumped to 18 µmol/L
in a matter of months,
though there is
a complicating factor.
His folate plunged
at the same time,
and folate is also necessary
to detoxify homocysteine.
Evidently, when he stopped
supplementing with B12,
he also stopped eating
as many fruits and vegetables,
folate
is concentrated in greens,
because it was wintertime
and his access was limited,
so that may have
contributed, too.
The bottom line,
the researchers concluded,
is that this
reiterates the need
for continuous
B12 supplementation
in persons following
an unfortified plant-based diet.
Some medical professionals
even suggest
it might be
a good preventative measure
for all vegans to annually
check their B12 status.
The number one question
primary care doctors
are advised to ask
symptomatic patients
on a plant-based diet is,
“What Is Your Preferred
Source of Vitamin B12?”